<!--  StdFF.xml                                          Frank Lübeck  -->

<Chapter Label="ch:StdFF">
<Heading>Standard finite fields</Heading>

<Section Label="sec:StdFFIntro">
<Heading>Definition of standard finite fields</Heading>

In <Cite Key="StdFFCyc" /> we define  for each prime <M>p</M> and positive
integer <M>n</M> a standardized model for the finite field with <M>p^n</M>
elements. This is done by defining  for each prime <M>r</M> polynomials of
degree <M>r</M> which define <M>r</M>-power  extensions of the prime field
<M>GF(p)</M> and by combining these for all <M>r | n</M> in a unique tower
of finite fields where the successive degrees are non-decreasing primes.
<P/>
This construction  has the nice property  that whenever <M>n |  m</M> then
the tower basis of  the field with <M>p^n</M> elements is  a subset of the
tower basis of  the field with <M>p^m</M> elements (as  monomials over the
prime field <M>GF(p)</M>).
<P/>
Via  this   construction  each  element   in  the  algebraic   closure  of
<M>GF(p)</M> can be identified by its degree <M>d</M> over the prime field
and  its  Steinitz number  in  the  field  with <M>p^d</M>  elements  (see
section&nbsp;<Ref Sect="sec:DefTower"/> for definitions of the tower basis
and the Steinitz numbers).
<P/>
Since arithmetic in simple algebraic  extensions is more efficient than in
iterated extensions we also provide  the field with <M>p^n</M> elements as
simple extension with  efficient maps from and to  the tower construction.
For this we use a standardized  primitive element of the construction (the
sum of the generators of the maximal subfields of prime power degree).
</Section>

<Section Label="sec:CreateFF">
<Heading>Creating standard finite fields</Heading>

<#Include Label="FF">
<#Include Label="IsFF">

</Section>

<Section Label="sec:ElementsFF">
<Heading>Elements in standard finite fields</Heading>

For  fields in  <Ref  Filt="IsStandardFiniteFieldTower"/> we  can use  all
functions  described  in section  <Ref  Sect="sec:TowerFun"/>  to map  its
elements to and from polynomials, vectors with respect to the tower basis,
or Steinitz numbers.
<P/>
For fields in <Ref  Filt="IsStandardFiniteField"/> we provide functions to
map their elements to and from  the corresponding tower elements, and also
shortcuts for the maps to and from vectors and Steinitz numbers.
<P/>

<#Include Label="FFElmConv">

</Section>

<Section Label="sec:FFEmbed">
<Heading>Embeddings of standard finite fields</Heading>

For a  standard finite field <C>F</C>  and its tower <C>T  := Tower(F)</C>
the list  <C>GeneratorsOfField(T)</C> contains the residue  classes of the
indeterminates  defining  the  prime  power extensions  of  <C>T</C>.  Our
standardized primitive  element of any  subfield of  <C>T</C> is a  sum of
appropriate elements in this list of generators.
<P/>
The tower basis of <C>T</C> contains the tower basis of any subfield. This
yields a construction of canonical embeddings of all subfields of <C>F</C>
into  <C>F</C>.  And  one  can  easily  read  off  the  smallest  subfield
containing an element in <C>F</C>  or <C>T</C> from its coefficient vector
with respect to the tower basis.  Each element of the algebraic closure of
<C>FF(p,1)</C>  is uniquely  determined  by its  degree  <C>d</C> and  its
Steinitz number in <C>FF(p, d)</C>.

<#Include Label="SteinitzPair">
<#Include Label="FFEmbedding">
<#Include Label="StandardIsomorphismGF">

</Section>

</Chapter>

